Vivekpandian Veerapandian

Sunnyvale, CA vivekpandian08@gmail.com (214) 802-4843 github.com/vivekpandian08 website: vivekpandian08.github.io linkedin.com/in/vivekpandian8

Data Scientist with **3-years of experience** in extracting business insights from data points by building Linear and Non-Linear models. Equipped with in-depth knowledge and practice of deploying end-to-end machine learning models in the Cloud.

EDUCATION

M.S., Data Science and Business Analytics , The University of Texas at Dallas GPA: 3.67

Coursework: Statistics, Predictive Analytics, Econometrics, Time Series Forecasting, Machine Learning, Deep Learning

• Project Mentor, BALC: Mentored 15 Grad Students in an Intra College ML project competition, and secured 3rd place

B.E., Electronics and Communication, College of Engineering Guindy, India

May 2011

Dec 2020

SKILLS

Programming: Python (Scikit-learn, Pandas, Numpy, TensorFlow, PyTorch, Keras, OpenCV, PySpark), R, SQL, SAS

Data Visualization : Tableau, Power BI, Shiny, GGPlot2, Plotly, Matplotlib, Seaborn, Bokeh

Databases & Bigdata : BigQuery, MySQL, PostgreSQL, Oracle, Graph, MongoDB (NoSQL), Hadoop, Hive, Spark

ML Concepts : Hypothesis Testing, A/B Testing, Regression, Classification, Clustering, NLP, Computer Vision

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Senior Data Scientist, Ordermycake.in

Jan 2015 - June 2018

- Technologies: Python, R, MySQL, Tableau, AWS EC2, S3
- Generated **18% increase in revenue to \$5k** in 2017 by leveraging sentiment analysis, extracting topics and key phrases on customers feedback, and suggested a new payment method to solve delivery problems
- Designed 3 A/B tests to identify the most captivating marketing campaign, resulted in a 30% increase in sales
- Revamped coupon mailing strategy for 3 customer segments by clustering using K-means and identifying the most engaging coupons leading to a 12% estimated increase in headcount
- Identified 4500 potential churn customers by developing ML models and mitigated 36% by offering them discounts
- Recommended optimized price for products by web scraping and data mining to analyze competitor product prices,
 leading to a \$3K increase in yearly revenue
- Led a 10-member cross-functional team to build an end to end B2C platform to expand the operations from 2 to 8 cities

Software Engineer, Cluster Wireless Software

Mar 2012 – Sept 2014

- Technologies: MySQL, C
- Designed SQL queries to extract information from IoT sensor data and identified anomalies by K-means clustering
- Analyzed product pain points and collaborated with a multi-functional team to develop robust solutions to meet client requirements, increased project conversion to 30%

INTERNSHIP EXPERIENCE

Data Science Intern, SuperWorld, United States

Sept 2020 - Present

- Technologies: R, Python, Google Analytics
- Built **Predictive model** using Decision Tree to find the likelihood of a purchase from clickstream data and optimize the model by adding new features to improve the precision rate to 76%

PERSONAL PROJECTS (DATA SCIENCE)

Stress Detection on Social Media

Python (Natural Language Processing)

- Leveraged web scrapping to scrape 30k labeled Reddit posts and extracted features by pre-training Word2Vec, Doc2Vec and BERT embeddings with 190k unlabeled posts that capture semantic and syntactic similarity among words
- Trained XGBoost and BERT models to classify Stress posts on GCP, that achieved accuracy of 92.74% and recall of 94.58%

Traffic Sign Recognition for Autonomous Driving

Python (Computer Vision)

- Pre-processed images and experimented with 5 different CNN architectures using Tensorflow to classify 43 traffic signs
- Deployed an interactive web APP that classifies traffic sign from user input using Flask(REST API) and Kubernetes on GCP

Credit Card Fraud Detection

Python (Supervised Learning)

Performed data analysis, and hypothesis testing. Built an ML pipeline using python(PySpark) to predict fraud transaction using SVM, KNN, Naïve Bayes, Random Forest, and Neural Networks with SMOTE resampling and achieved AUC of 0.82